there's an interesting set of questions
we received which basically pertains to
the way to prepare yourself to practice
how to practice and then also how to
look for the right environment for your
practice and as we here as we covered
most of those things in various talks he
would probably be it would be a good
idea to mention it all together in one
one specific talk and then people who do
go through our other other recorded
their videos on YouTube then they can
also refer to those as well as the
question specifies since how to
establish the right knowledge base for
three things
feeding suitors developer develop a
reflexive mindset which is a mindset of
mindfulness and advice um entering game
on a stream where you can obviously
perfect these these practices mm-hmm so
the the first point is how to read the
sutras correctly it comes down to
recognizing it whichever way you start
it will not be perfect because you're
already starting with all the wrong
views wrong assumptions and then you
won't be able to to begin in a manner
that won't be revolving around those so
the reason why it's important to
maintain that as a context is because to
prevent you from drifting too far away
from the original motivation that made
you want to practice which is suffering
and freedom from it so you recognize
that it's your experience as it is at
the very starting point that's where the
problem is so then whatever you're
learning through the suitors through the
instruction of another as in the form of
privileged teachers or whatever the
point is whatever you're learning about
it you will then maintain the correct
context in recognizing that whatever
you're learning about it it should be
pertaining to undoing that wrong
starting point
of your your state of group of your
state of Utah Jeana otherwise what's
gonna happen is if you don't question
your starting point you will take for
granted all of your attitudes and
notions about the practice about the
things that you should be practicing
with you'll be taking them for granted
as if they are not already affected with
ignorance and then you will be trying to
build your practice on top of those and
that's why it won't be won't work so for
example it's it's like say say you come
across the suitors for the first time
and you start reading the translation of
the suitors which is you know there's no
problem there but and then it talks
about the consciousness talks about the
matter see the problem there is that
when you think consciousness when you
think method when when mine affected
with ignorance thinks consciousness
that's not that which consciousness is
or rather it might be to some extent but
already those notions are the notions
effective with ignorant so instead of
you thinking that you can understand the
surface just by figuring out or the
relationship between consciousness or
this so that when you are thinking
consciousness or form and trying to
figure things out on account of it those
terms are already the terms that are
affected with ignorance so that's that's
a very important point here is the
practice the direction of the practice
is the direction of undoing your current
understanding the understanding at a
starting point of of what consciousness
is what your experience is where the
relationship with with with others we
agreed a virgin delusional so it's not
about finding the secret that's been
hitting away from you
it's really removing the the assumptions
and notions and significance is that you
yourself have been maintaining that have
been obscuring the nature of those
things so the nature of those things is
properly understood not at the end where
you figure it all out but in the very
beginning basically when you undo all
the wrong notions they've been covering
it up if you keep that in mind then the
attitude of reading the suttas will be
much well it won't be too too wrong to
begin with so when you're reading
something about the culture
very nimble or any suit them whichever
so do your reading of whatever it might
be about you will then maintain a notion
that if you truly understand the suitor
you will be at least a sort of honor if
you fully understand and develop that
the suitor and fully then develop the
understanding you've been out of hand
so when you have a notion that you
understood the suit that is absolutely
fine because you probably did understand it
because you probably did understand it
to some extent but unless then you know
for sure that your understanding is on
the level of freeing you from suffering
and preventing you from being able to
suffer even amidst things they used to
cause you suffering so unless your
understanding is reach their level you
shouldn't really be content with it you
shouldn't really think that you
understood it because understanding
you've done rightly results in freedom
from suffering automatically so that is
always your criteria to go back to and
then the efforts towards contemplation
of understanding the instruction
clarifying getting the meaning of the
instruction for practice those efforts
should be then revolving around not as I
said not figuring it out as something
you're missing out but more like
questioning the things that you are
using to figure these things out so when
you are thinking about what is the
nature of what is like a nature of an
otter for example when you say to
yourself okay an otter means this maybe
you can solve Polly consult other
translations and then you get the idea
of what an artist but instead using that
idea to sort of arrive at some
conclusion you really want to be keep
questioning that idea as much as you can
and go in the opposite direction not and
arrive at a conclusion but undo any
assumption you have about it so you can
take em you can literally take any Polly
term for example and reflect on it like
that and you're relevant Polly tale so
if you take the say for example Rupa in
the Sutra see it means form it means
just like this form is matter sometimes
means body so do you know what that
means when you yourself in your own
experience when you say Rupa when you
say matter or whichever your native
language is whichever word you will be
using instead of assuming that you
already know what it means what you
designate it with that word start
questioning it so when you say like
count his consciousness like unconscious what
his consciousness like unconscious what
does that mean to you
can you describe can you see what is it
that you refer to when you use a
designation called consciousness what
are you referring to in your experience
because you must be referring something
otherwise that word would be completely
meaningless all the words would be
completely meaningless so that's how you
should be reading the suitors as well
you read the sentence you read it - you
kind of understand it but then see how
deeply can you question that
understanding while you read in that
suit there
when the Buddha paints offense a
scenario of like a young man subject to
their subject that he does this and then
he goes forth and then you take take
every individual sentence and then
reflect on it in the direction that I
just outlined question it so when it
says in the sutras or young man
experience dissatisfaction with life at
MIT MIT experience in the satisfaction
way what do I take for granted that I've
already understood properly what
dissatisfaction for life is I'm sure I
might have understood it to some extent
but what is what is it to say am I able
to say correctly that I understood it to
the same extent like this young man in
the solicitor would refer you and then
you question it so don't thank you for
granted so even even for things that
generic is dissatisfaction with life you
can access the same reflexive sort of
contemplation and questioning let alone
then for the more specific terms like an
art time dukkha and all those all those
other other key phrases from the suitors
so that's that's how you because that's
how you come to understand them is
discerning them removing the the
gratuitous assumptions so you get to
discern them on the level of your own
experience because these things are
universal the suitors are basically just
the most accurate descriptions of the
universal aspect of every human
experience that's it so whether they
were they were spoken to in a half
millennia they were spoken five
millennia ago
then if they were spoken 10 years ago if
you were spoken correctly they would
have always be pertaining to the same
universal principles which means doesn't
matter how much time passes between the
utterance of the suitors and in one
understanding them one will be
understanding the same things and even
the Buddha himself was could not have
done things differently he himself said
that all that the targeter can do is
uncover the universal truth the
universal path that has always been
there just been covered up like a jungle
overgrown the old ancient path so
keeping that in mind then you realize
it's not about it arriving at something
you're missing out it's really
uncovering the place where you begin
your practice from so you want to
practice now the direction sort of
collecting information from out there
that's all fine you need to know what
you're at least supposed to do but then
once you start doing it it's basically
about removing they're questioning the
assumptions that you already have in
regards to things that you are using for
your practice so when you say when you
read a suit about meditation upon
certain types of perceptions you start
asking yourself ok perception when I say
perception what am i referring to am i
referring to sight sounds now how does
that what are the characteristics what
are the signs and tokens is the widow
would say all those things did I will
automatically take for granted if I
start looking at the answers that they
will be provided for me but it's not
about the answer it's about questioning
the premises of your questions even
before you arrive at any answers so with
that kind of attitude the suitors will
then start to serve as basically not as
some sort of information on instruction
but there's a direct most accurate most
most immediate description of the
universal aspects of your experience
here and now of everyone else's
experience here and now being in the
past or in the future because that's how
accurate sutras are but the reason why
one is not able to understand them to
the point of developing the right view
is
of your own wrong views and wrong
assumptions so wrong assumption about
consciousness about the five agree it's
about everything that you readings in
the suitors most of the things already
are infected with your own assumptions
that is your starting point so it's not
to figure out the secret that's
contained in the sutras it's basically
undoing your assumptions about the
concepts that you read and that's how
you can get to understand what those
concepts refer to what it's going to do
what their nature is and that's how in
the sutras you get sometimes a person
literally here is a sentence of from the
Buddha to and immediately becomes a sort
of banner it's no because he was so
lucky and the Buddha a sort of planted
the truth in his head with using his
psychic powers so he said himself the
target I cannot do the work for you he
can point out the way if you make the
effort you'll arrive at the right view
in other hand ship if not you want
doesn't matter what the director says so
the reason why those people would need
such a little amount of instructure is
because they did not carry all these
wrong assumptions in regard to
terminology they just heard Buddha utter
so that that explains all those cases
when like people upon hearing one so
that's it they became adamant means
they'd already done the work of removing
these assumptions or certainly haven't
done the wrong work of accumulating
these assumptions so how far your
assumptions have been accumulated you
can tell the only way to know that is in
hindsight once you have gone down there
so that's how you should read the sutras
so the second point then is how to
develop the practice mindfulness
properly how to develop this reflects a
mind set in brief the fundamental
attitude for properly practice
mindfulness is being aware of the
motivation behind your current actions
whatever those actions might be
it's not about attending to your body
observing sensations and whatnot it's
really maintaining that background
knowledge of what is currently happening
to you which
always involves a degree of your action
to some extent so that's the basic
principle mindfulness is simply asking
yourself what am i doing right now what
am i doing right now you will already
know what you're doing without needing
to stop doing what you're doing
so the mindfulness is on the level of
discerning that knowledge that's already
there that's why if you do mindfulness
correctly it is effortless as we spoke
so many times and the so the reflexive
mindset then is the mindset that keeps
watchful eye not only immediacy of your
experiences and I'm touching now my legs
and I'm sitting and I'm leaning you
don't need to be saying all those things
because you're already doing them all
you need to do is find the elevated
ground from which those things will be
seen without needing to directly stare
at them and that elevated ground is the
is the motivation behind your current
action or the relevant elevated ground
can then be rooted in anything else that
that acts as a basis for your action
where your motivations are rooted body
postures current moods feelings and so
on so it's important the important thing
is to think that to realize that it's
not about trying to catch a moment and
be so attentive to to one moment so you
don't miss anything out the point is
actually completed the opposite
direction which is direction of knowing
what you're already doing without
needing to directly attend and keep
telling yourself what you're doing could
you already know what you doing that's
the that's the key here
you're not fabricating their knowledge
your discerning it has already being
there and without that kind of knowledge
of what's already happening to you to
something doesn't mean you fully
understood it that means there is
already a degree of some recognition and
that's basically what mindfulness is
that's why I kind of too much
mindfulness you have to you can't have
too much of a recognition of what's
already happening to you what you're
already doing what you want to do and
that's also why if you practice
mindfulness like that it will you will
become well it will it will become it
will become impossible to not see where
things that you are about to do where
those things are routed you will you
won't be able to mistakenly or
carelessly engage with unwholesome you
will only be able to do so volitional
and knowingly cuz now you know the one
that's what ignorance is the most
fundamental ignoring choosing to ignore
what you know choosing do you know
what's already there choosing to ignore
the certain motivation behind your
action that you know we're actually
rooted in desire or ill-will and so on
and you will be able to maintain that
kind of choice of ignoring because you
don't have developed you haven't
practiced mindfulness efficiently enough
you haven't developed it but if now your
standard is to never be completely
ignorant of your current situation
current motivation current actions means
you will never be able to fully
completely commit them to choosing to
ignore it so that you can follow your
desire your ill will and and distraction
and that's the key here
all of those unwholesome things are
always rooted in your intention to do
them you can't accidentally two things
rooted in desire aversion and delusion
that's why you are responsible for it
that's where the Buddha would say things
like you must then avoid everything
unwholesome and then cultivate the
wholesome that's the key it's rooted in
the knowledge it's through the
recognition and that's what ignorant
comes first
you can only ignore something that's
already there you can't ignore things
that don't exist so a certain
recognition exists when you choose to
ignore it and that's why person is fully
responsible for a major a VJ is not on
the level of a metaphysical secret that
needs to be figured out a VJ is the most
immediate attitude that you have toward
your own experience as a whole attitude
of ignoring it that's it
attitude of taking for granted there is
in desire there is an aversion and so on
by doing actions by performing actions
rooted in attitude of ignoring your own
experience that's how you maintain the
ignoring of your experience so first you
need to practice sense restraint
restrained develop virtue as in stop
maintaining the wrong attitude through
those unwholesome actions and then you
can develop proper mindfulness of their
attitude because it is already there
whatever you are doing right now the
motivation to do that the intention to
do that is simultaneously present with
it on that level of the knowledge I
still have an intention to carry on
sitting here and answering these
questions once that intention changes as
in once I decide not to do it anymore
I'll stop doing it and now I don't need
to be thinking about how am i sitting
and how my back is touching the chair
and so on because all of those things
are already contained within the
intention to do this action so that's
that's pretty much the only place you
need to keep your eye on you don't need
to monitor and try to catch all of these
little things that are happening around
you and control them no you just need to
keep an eye on the peripherally just
just be aware with the corner of your
eye on that point where the action is
rooted which is in the intention for
direction so if my intention changes and
starts going into something unwholesome
I would see it even before you even
start doing anything remotely also and
if you see it as as the level of that
possibility of unwholesome means it's
not a new so you just it's enough to
recognize it at that level and you won't
be acting out of it if you choose to act
out of it it cannot be accidental mmm
you will do so intentionally and that's
the thing the more you develop
mindfulness the less able you will be to
intentionally engage with unwholesome
actions that's where literally the
Buddha sometimes to some people this was
so clear to some people that he could
all he needed to say was avoid
everything that you know to be
unwholesome and cultivate everything
that you know as in you're aware of it
with the corollary are your seeing
whether the intention is wholesome or
unwholesome and cultivate everything
that's wholesome and that's it people
contemplated like that practice that
kind of attitude and became other hands
because you cannot have greed aversion
delusion persist in your mind unless
it's being maintained unless it's being
perpetuated and fed with the bodily
action verbal action and mental
elections so once you have uprooted the
intentionally choosing those types of
actions these things will have to fade
away out of your mind they cannot remain
there whether you want it or not it
doesn't matter that's a similar with
what I said if if if if a hand sits on
her legs even if she doesn't wish for
her chicken to pierce through the shell
safely and come into this world they
will because she's sitting on her eggs
and if the other hand doesn't sit on her
eggs even if she wishes oh may my chicks
even if she wishes oh may my chicks
pierce out safely they won't because
she's not sitting on sex so even if a
monk wishes that his mind be purified
from unwholesome he won't be unless he's
doing the work if he's doing the world
even if he doesn't wishes that his mind
result in liberation and purify from her
wholesome he will because he's doing the
world so that's the reflexive attitude
just keep a corner of your eye to
whatever you're currently doing wherever
your current actions are rooted in but
it's passively enduring things done to
you experiencing witnessing whether
you're actively doing fundamentally
there is a certain intention ality
involved in all of that and that's on
the level of knowledge you already know
what your situation is to put it in a
most general term that's where body
postures are kind of natural anchors as
a natural foundation for whatever's
happening to you
so whatever is happening to me now so
the basis that this body is seated
though you don't need to be attending to
see the body you just need to know that
you're already seated and then that
knowledge in doers you don't need to
keep repeating I'm sitting I'm sitting
what am i doing now what's what's my
body posture now it's seated okay so now
there's this knowledge that I have
established by answering it and this
knowledge is still here and we can talk
about different things now we can
address different topics but the corner
of my eyes still kept on the on the
basis of the background that this body
remains seated so whatever happens it it
will happen on the basis of being
anchored in the seated position that's
it so you want to actually you don't
have to keep repeating and telling
yourself I'm seated I'm seated you want
to bring your mind to it show
but discern it peripherally and then let
let other things occur let your mind go
without you losing the sight that you
are still seated so the keys to start
discerning that relationship between
things you are attending and the
background those things are rooted in
inevitable what you wanted or not so I'm
still seated
so my situation of having a seated body
while we are talking about all these
things has remain unchanged for like
what half an hour now 20-something
minutes it isn't may not changed and
your awareness can then come and go from
it but all you need to do is keep the
like 0.1% literally oh the background
it's just not completely drift away and
if you do drift away you can recognize
yourself for as long as the body remains
seated because the anchor has remained
unchanged so then in other words your
forgetfulness it's gonna start being
included in your mindful situation that
you have established with the knowledge
of it because lapsing of the mind as an
attention sort of going going going and
then losing sight of itself is
inevitable that's how the mind works but
it's when you remember whether you will
remember on the wrong basis or on the
right basis if you remember on the right
basis that's what I mean when I say you
will start forgetting things mindfully
in other words you can only forget the
content of the experience not the nature
anymore and that if you fully develop
that the mind will be impenetrable there
will be absolutely no greater resolution
left in it that's that's the mindfulness
developed to the extent necessary for
the final knowledge as the Buddha would
say it in satipatthana that kind of
knowledge will then be understood and
discerned as more fundamental even than
your act of forgetting this or
forgetting that so your forgetfulness
your active forgetting will build it
mindful you will do it mindfully and you
do it mindfully not when you overly
attend it and try to control it you did
mindfully where you become unable to to
misunderstand it that's it and unable to
infect it with your wrong assumption and
that's pretty much all to it once your
behavior has been restrained with the
rules and Verge
and precepts you don't want to be over
committing in trying to control the
content of your thought or all of your
actions you actually want to be
discerning the intention simultaneously
present with those things so I'm still
seated and we're still talking about it
and it's still the same mindfulness or
the same knowledge of the same seated
position and during all this time and
now if you have doubt for example but is
it is it not is it not that doubt cannot
actually do anything to the seated body
because for as long as the body pause
remain seated
the anchor of the discernment remains
unchanged so it becomes impenetrable to
doubt as well doubt will penetrate it
wherever you start doubting it and then
you stand up and then you start out and
what am i doing but again even that it's
you will intentionally choose to give in
to trying to appease the doubt as
opposed to not giving and maintain the
knowledge of the peripheral situation
that has remained unchanged so you go
beyond doubt when you stop feeding the
craving towards the doubt not when you
keep finding not when you find a perfect
answer that will appease the doubt once
and for all doubt is an attitude in
regard to the content which means nature
of that content is inherently
impenetrable by that doubt but you are
the one who chooses to ignore that and
feed the doubt by trying to provide the
answers that doubt is pressing you
towards that's why doubt is a hindrance and if
that's why doubt is a hindrance and if
you stop feeding it it will stop
exercising power over you
same as ready any other hindrance action
that question was the well choosing the
right environment the right monastry and
so on yeah you have to recognize the
limitations of early life the the
constant bombardment of engagements in
other people and company had to evolve
how to maintain solitude and so on so if
you if you choose to stay a layman or a
woman you have to take up responsibility
for it which means you have to take a
responsibility for for limiting the
extent you can develop your practice you
just you
can't do it in such an environment only
to some extent like back in the day when
when when lies were not so bombarded and
sensuality was not so accessible he was
still hard like you read it in the
sitter's you know people could get the
right view and so on but even back then
it was hard imagined today with
everything is like a finger click away
and constantly I mean like massive
massive people live in massive cities
with loads of Boulos constant crowd in a
part you just constant constant company
company even if you're not necessarily
perceiving it directly anymore it's
there it's part of the significance of
the society that you that you live in so
you have to recognize the limitations
and then take responsibility for it then
you can't really complain if your
practice is not really developing to the
extent you want to do because you chose
to stay in the moment that is such
having said that now that doesn't mean
that going get into monastery we a
solution in itself either basically
monastery is just intensifying
environment for the work you need to do
internally so if you're not doing the
work internally doesn't matter if you
spend the rest of your life in the
monastery you won't go you won't get
anywhere so sometimes people think that
all you only need to do is find a
perfect monastery and the practice will
everything will fall into place and they
will just be sailing but that's that's
completely completely not the case so
the suitability of a monastery should be
measured to the extent of whether you
are able to maintain the virtue as in
whether the community is keeping the
Avena arrows to the extent of whether
you were just constantly engaging with
laypeople and constantly sitting in the
organized groups and crowds and
community meetings and community things
and doing things together or whether you
actually spend most of the day left
alone as in in solitude doesn't mean
left alone without any instruction and
so on that means that whether most of
your time is in the environment is
within the environment they will they
will provide a physical solitude now
sure there are things occasion you come
together but you want sort of to
constitute mine a part of the day when
if everybody's perfectly silent in
mindful the fact is you're surrounded
physically by others there's perception
of others
and because of that the mind won't be
taking developing notions and signs of
Solitude there the necessary to discern
the sign of the mind there is necessary
to discern the right view and sort of
party so so the criteria is put in the
right place a relatively general so the
winner and solitude everything else in
between you know when there is a will
there is a way things are not perfect
you could still make it work as long as
these fundamental principles are not
compromised so it's important to really
see that there is no such thing as a
perfect place because you're absolutely
no criteria what perfection is you're
only the criteria of proteges now who
starts practicing or even some of these
practicing longer or something but who's
not sold upon the criteria is that this
pleases me and this displeases me as the
suitor often say as the suitors often
say so you don't really you shouldn't
really be trusting that if something is
pleasing to you that's all that means
that it's right or that if something is
displaced into it means that it's wrong
nobody denies that you will be
experiencing things in such manner but
instead of just taking for granted your
attitude towards it question it so if
there's something displeasing to use the
questioning why is this did the Buddha
say this is wrong or why am i funny this
displeasing are my ideals that are not
matched by whatever like all these
things are my ideals right but is this
behavior against the Vinaya is this
environment against the practice maybe
if so then okay you got your answer if
it isn't then like so why is still this
presentation because people you know
Minds everyone's mind to some extent
will be looking for faults in things as
well so we looking for faults which
should be revolving around could see
thought that's where that self honesty
has to be important and even if things
are overall displeasing to you unless
the criterias of inner and solitude are
compromised then you really should try
and work with it as opposed to just
going from a monastery to a monastery or
a place to place or refusing to commit
to it because you still haven't found a
perfect situation
you'll never will because the perfect
situation will be created from the
inside on a certain sufficient basis
the perfect situation won't be found
outside otherwise all you need to do is
get to monastery to become an element
and everybody will be doing that so I
think that kind of sums up in general
the attitude towards the suitors the
attitude towards my influence which is
necessary for discernment and then
tailoring that those criteria for
towards search for the right environment
even if you don't necessarily commit to
the monastery
you can certainly simplify your life as
a layman of keeping the precepts reduce
the amount of time you eat per day don't
eat for beautification don't eat for the
pleasure of the taste but literally
measure recognize the necessity for
micronutrients for health for strength
for endurance and then meet the
micronutrients in the most efficient way
and micronutrients as well for that
matter but let's not get into that now
but the point is don't don't just you
could practice lots of restraint you
could practice you could set up
relatively sufficient environment unless
you're only committed to life in terms
of family and everything else in which
case it'll be even harder but you could
set up even your your your lay
environment to a great deal by
simplifying your life and that can
certainly help you then and offer is a
kind of a transitional step if you are
still unsure whether you want to do in
the monastery and so on so mmm yeah
being aware of your situation will then
enable you to judge these things rightly
and practice sense restraint accordingly